Guide to the Josephine Campbell papers, 1905-2006 MS2237
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Josephine Campbell papers
1905-2006
1947-2006
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Campbell, Josephine C.
United States Information Agency
Ecotopics International News Service
Campbell, Carolyn M.
MS2237
5.5 Linear Feet 5 document boxes, 3 flat boxes
This collection contains manuscripts, notebooks, correspondence, newspaper clippings, periodicals, pamphlets, maps, photographs, slides, negatives, microcassette tapes, floppy discs, and various digital records related to the life and work of Josephine "Jo" Campbell (1927-2006), journalist, civil rights worker, and environmentalist.
Restrictions on Access
This collection is open for research.
Custodial History
Josephine Campbell's papers were intially transferred into the custody of her daughter Carolyn Campbell, who donated the collection to the George Washington University Gelman Library.
Acquisition Source
Gift of Carolyn M. Campbell, 19 November 2007 (Accession 2008.038)
Scope and Contents
This collection contains manuscripts, notebooks, correspondence, newspaper clippings, periodicals, pamphlets, photographs, slides, negatives, microcassette tapes, floppy discs, and various digital records. The materials range in date from 1947 to 2006 and represent the history of Josephine Campbell's career as journalist. Campbell was a writer and editor with the United State Information Agency from 1956-1986 and later founded Ecotopics International News Service. Her early work is represented, but the bulk of materials pertain to her research and writing for Ecotopics. Significant topics represented in the collection include international journalism; environmental issues; feminism; and human rights.
Collection Arrangement
Organized into 3 series: Writings, Research, and Correspondence, Photographs, and Digital Materials.
Biographical Note
Josephine "Jo" Campbell (1927-2006) was journalist, civil rights worker, and environmental activist. She was born Josephine Anne Conrad in Evansville, Indiana on January 31, 1927, the daughter of Owen McIntyre Conrad and Josephine Anne Greene. She was raised by her mother in Daytona Beach, Florida. She attended Seabreeze High School while working as a "cub reporter" for the Daytona Beach News Journal, and after her graduation in 1945 she moved to Washington, D.C. to further her career in journalism as a copyboy for the Washington Post.
Josephine Conrad married Donald Herman Campbell on March 15, 1946. The couple had three daughters, Kathleen, Carolyn, and Deborah Campbell.
Campbell wrote fiction for magazines under her husband's name, worked in public relations, and headed the Washington bureau of a Pakistani newspaper before beginning her 30 year career with the International Press Service, part of the Department of State's U.S. Information Agency in 1956. As a writer and editor for IPS, she travelled in the United States and Africa and wrote for Voice of America and publications in Africa, Russia, and the Middle East until her retirement in 1986.
After her husband's death in 1988, Campbell founded Ecotopics International News Service, a news service for environmental and human rights issues. She and her partner, chemist Hyman Rudoff, wrote for Ecotopics as well as the local Willits News in California. She was also active the National Writers Union, the National Press Club, the Dog Writers Association of America, the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, the American Civil Liberties Union, and the Ukiah Gun Club.
Josephine Campbell died March 1, 2006 in Petaluma, California.
DVDs; Microcassettes; Human rights advocacy; Environmentalism; Journalism; Floppy disks; Negatives (photographic); Color slides; Photographs; United States. Dept. of State. International Press Service; Campbell, Carolyn M.
- Writings, Research, and Correspondence, 1905-2006; 1947-2006; Series 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains manuscripts, notebooks, correspondence, newspaper clippings, periodicals, pamphlets, maps. They range in dates from 1905 to 2006 and represent her work as a journalist for the United States Information Agency from 1956 to 1986 and Ecotopics International News Service, which she founded after her retirement from USIA. Also included is early fiction writing, submitted to magazines under her husband's name, and correspondence from publishers. Files contain published and unpublished samples of Campbell's work along with many of her notes and research materials. The series also contains some writing by Campbell's partner, Dr. Hyman Rudoff. Significant topics represented in this series include international journalism; environmental issues; feminism; and human rights.
  - Black History/Justine Bonner, 1976-1998; 1995-1998; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Computer Mags, Re: Submissions, 1985-1987; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cornell Breast Cancer Research, circa 1995-1997; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1983-2003; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Early Writing [1/6], 1947-1952; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Early Writing [2/6], 1947-1952; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Early Writing [3/6], 1947-1952; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Early Writing [4/6], 1947-1952; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Early Writing [5/6], 1947-1952; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Early Writing [6/6], 1947-1952; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Eco Research, 1979-1998; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ecotopics #12, 2003; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - General Correspondence & Writing Samples [1/3], 1995-2006; MS2237 Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - General Correspondence & Writing Samples [2/3], 1987-2006; MS2237 Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence & Writing Samples [3/3], 1980-2006; MS2237 Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - International Feminist Planning Conference, 1973 June; MS2237 Series 1 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1980-2001; MS2237 Series 1 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Research, 1957, 1993-2003; 1993-2003; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Nathaniel Green (Ancestor), 1927-2000; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Nelson Bond, 1997; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - News Clippings, 1996-2003; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - NOW International Feminist Planning Conference, 1974; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    File contains two copies of conference proceedings from the National Organization for Women International Feminist Planning Conference, held June 1-4, 1973 in Cambridge, Massuchusetts.
    General
    Josephine Campbell attended the 1973 NOW International Feminist Planning Conference, where she interviewed Yoko Ono and shared a luncheon table with Ono and her husband John Lennon.
  - Obituaries, 2006; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Obituaries, 2006; MS2237 Series 1 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Obituaries, 2006; MS2237 Series 1 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Owning a Dog, 2000; MS2237 Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Personal Files, 1990-2002; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Podiatry Study, 2002; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Poetry, 1978, circa 1995; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - The Poet's Domain, 1994; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Poultry Industry Investigation [1/2], 1995-1997; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Poultry Industry Investigation [2/2], 1995-1997; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Professional Files, 1974-2006; MS2237 Series 1 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Published Poetry [1/2], 1994-1996; MS2237 Series 1 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Published Poetry [2/2], 1994-1996; MS2237 Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Reporter's Notebooks [1/4], 1995-1996; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Reporter's Notebooks [2/4], 1997; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Reporter's Notebooks [3/4], 2004-2006; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Reporter's Notebooks [4/4], undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - The Shore Journal, 1995-1998; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Wilhelm Weinberg Seminar [1/2], circa 1978-1981, 2005; 1978-1981; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Wilhelm Weinberg Seminar [2/2], circa 1978-1981; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Writing [1/2], 1973-2001; MS2237 Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Writing [2/2], 1980-2006; MS2237 Series 1 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Writing Samples [1/3], 1977-1982; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Writing Samples [2/3], 1981, 1989-1999; 1989-1999; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Writing Samples [3/3], 2002-2006; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Oversize Items, 1905-circa 1961; Series 1 (Box 5)
- Photographs and Audiovisual Content, 1975-1998; Series 2
  Series Arrangement
  Photographs are arranged first alphabetically. Audiovisual content follows.
  The materials in this series include photographs, slides, negatives, cassettes, and microcassettes. They range in dates from 1975 to 1998 and represent Josephine Campbell's career as a journalist during that period. Campbell retired from the United States Information Agency in 1986 and later founded Ecotopics International News Service. Many of the photographs and other audiovisual materials depict Campbell at work, her colleagues, and the subjects she interviewed, including Congressman Steny Hoyer and journalist Dorothy Gilliam. Also included are slides of Campbell's travels in Africa from 1975 to 1977 for USIA, photographs of her coverage of the Nigerian Olympic team in 1984, and images related to her work in social and environmental activism.The microcassettes are recorded interviews of unknown subjects by Campbell. The cassettes are recordings related to Campbell's reporting on the International Feminist Planning Conference in 1973.
  - African Girl, undated; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - African-American Heritage Festival/Jo at Work, circa 1994-1995; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Agriculture, undated; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Black History/Justine Bonner, circa 1998; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Bob Latswaw, circa 1998; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Cornell Breast Cancer Research, circa 1997; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Crime Victims Ceremony, circa 1997; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Dorothy Gilliam, 1977; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Dr. Hyman Rudoff, undated; MS2237 Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Friends Christmas 1997, Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Jimmy Carter with African Diplomats, 1977-1978; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Jo Campbell, undated; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Jo Campbell -- Baltimore Times, undated; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Jo Campbell interviews J.J. Hill, Steny Hoyer, 1987; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Josephine Campbell, undated; MS2237 Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - News Service Coworkers, undated; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - 1984 Olympics, Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - 1984 Olympics, Nigerian Athlete, Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Pow Wow, circa 1993-1994; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Travels in Africa, 1975-1977; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Women's ERA Conference, 1997; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Women's "Green" Conference, Ocean City, MD, 1998; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Cassettes, c. 1973; MS2237 Series 2 (Box 7)
  - Microcassettes, 1997-2003; MS2237 Series 2 (Box 7)
- Digital Materials, circa 1994-2006; Series 3 (Box 8, Box 7)
  Restrictions on Access
  Access to digital records on the external hard drive is restricted; use access DVDs in box 7.
  The materials in this series include various digital records on 3.5 inch floppy disks, DVD, and external hard drive. They range in dates from circa 1994-2006 and represent Josephine Campbell's activities as a journalist for Ecotopics International News Service during that period. Digital records on floppy disk include digital photographs and possibly word processing documents. The external hard drive contains a range of files related to Campbell's work and family life, including digital photographs, text files, word processing documents, and music.
  Series: Arranged by media type.